<document><page number="1">[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
1 
 MALAYSIA  
IN THE HIGH COURT OF SABAH AND SARAWAK  
AT KOTA KINABALU  
CRIMINAL APPEAL NO. BKI -42LB -7/7 OF 2019  
BETWEEN  5 
PUBLIC PROSECUTOR            &#8230; APPELLANT  
AND  
  ADELINE CASIMIR YAPP                           &#8230; RESPOND ENT 
 
GROUNDS OF DECISION  10 
 
INTRODUCTION   
[1]       At the Session Court , there are two charges against the 
Respondent  under s.  408 of the Penal Code.  At the end of the 
Prosecution&#8217;s case, the trial Judge  discharged and acquitted the 15 
Respondent  from the two charges without calling for her defence.  
 
[2]      Dissatisfied with  the order,  the Appellant now appeals to this Court 
on the 2nd Charge only. For the convenient of reference, the parties will 
be referred as they w ere in the Court below.  The 2nd Charge  is as 20 
follows:  
&#8220;Bahawa kamu pada 14hb September 2017, bertempat di                          
FM Autohaus Sdn. Bhd ., di d alam daerah Kota Kinabalu, di dalam 
Negeri Sabah, sebagai seorang pengurus yang diamanahkan atas 
sifatnya dengan harta syarikat iaitu wang tunai bayaran pelanggan 25 
berjumlah RM9452.40 telah melakukan pecah amanah  jenayah 
iaitu menjadikan harta itu bagi kegunaan sendiri dengan itu k amu 
telah melakukan satu kesalahan yang boleh dihukum d i bawah 
Seksyen 408 Kanun Kese ksaan&#8221; . 




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
2 
 THE LAW  
[3]    Section 408 of the Penal Code  provides that:  
  &#8220;Criminal breach of trust by clerk or servant &#8221; 
 Whoever, being a clerk or servant, or employed as a clerk or 
servant, and being in any manner entrusted in  such capacity with 5 
property, or with any dominion over property, commits criminal 
breach of trust in respect of that property, shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which shall not less than one year and 
more than fourteen years and with whipping , and shall also be 
liable to fine.  10 
 
[4] The ingredients under section 408 of the Penal Code can be 
referred to Ratantlal &amp; Dhirajlal&#8217;s Law of Crime.  A Commentary on 
the Indian Penal Code, 1860, 27th Edition Abridged &amp; Updated : 
     &#8220;The ingredients of section 408 are:  15 
i. the accused must be a clerk or servant;  
ii. he must have been entrusted with property, or dominion 
over property; and  
iii. he must have committed criminal breach of tr ust in 
respect of such property . 20 
 
PETITION OF APPEAL  
[5] In his Petition of Appea l, the Appellant put forth the following 
grounds (verbatim) : 
a. that the Learned Session Court Judge erred in law and in 25 
fact in discharging and acquitting the Respondent for the                            
2nd charge as sufficient evidence has been adduced to prove 
that the Respo ndent had committed the offence;  
 




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
3 
 b. that the Learned Session Court Judge erred in law and in 
fact when satisfied that the Appellant had failed to prove 
prima facie case against the Respon dent for the 2nd charge;  
 
c. that the Learned Session Court Judge erred in law and in 5 
fact when failing to consider the evidence of PW8 that he did 
gave RM11,027.20 the Respondent;  
 
d. that the Learned Session Court Judge erred in law and in 
fact when failing to consider exhibit P4 that shows that the 10 
amount of RM11.027.20 that PW8 had given to the 
Respondent;  and 
 
e. that the Learned Session Court Judge erred in law and in 
fact when failing to consider that the Respondent had 15 
received RM11.027.20 the Respondent failed to hand over 
the money to the company . 
 
WHETHER PRIMA FACIE CASE HAD BEEN ADDUCED?  
[6] In order to establish a prima facie case, the prosecution                           20 
must adduce credible evidence proving each ingredient of the offence 
which if unrebutted or unexplained would warrant a conviction                               
(s.180 of the Criminal Procedure Code ).  
 
[7] The test of prima facie case as pronounced in the case of                               25 
PP v. Mohd. Radzi bin Abu Bakar  [2006] 1 CLJ 457  is as follows:  
&#8220;&#8230; ask yourself the question: If I now call upon the accused 
to make his defence and he elects to remain silent am                         
I prepared to convict him on the evidence now before me?                




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
4 
 If the answer to that question is "Yes", then a pr ima facie case 
has been made out and the defence should be called. If the 
answer is "No" then, a prima facie case has not been made 
out and the accused should be acquitted&#8221; .  
 5 
[8] I shall accordingly subject the evidence of the prosecution to the 
above test. 
 
[9] The crux of the matter is whether the Prosecution had proof that 
the accused have committed criminal breach of trust in respect of 10 
such property in the sum of RM9452.40.  
 
 [10] The Prosecution (Appellant) submit that the accused has been 
entrusted with the customer&#8217;s monies when the Accused receiv ed from 
PW 8. Moreover,  P4 (1) and (2)  clearly shows that the amount payable 15 
RM11,027.20 that the cu stomer need to pay and  P4 (9) the invoice show 
that Total RM11,000. However, the Accused has failed to hand over the 
full amount that the customer&#8217;s paid to the Accused. The Accused only 
hand over the money for vehicle SAA8886W  in the sum of RM1,547.60 
and the balance RM9452.40 had been breached by the Accu sed.  20 
 
[11]  The Prosecution called PW 8 with regards to  vehicle  SAA8886W  
and rely to the following testimonies of PW  8 to support that the payment 
of RM11,027.20 was paid to the A ccused : 
(lines 16-19 at page 161  of Record of Appeal)  25 
Q15 Adakah kamu masih ingat berapakah jumlah pembayaran 
bagi tujuan pembaikan SAA8886W tersebut?  
A I cannot recall the exact amount tapi dalam amount 
RM11,000.00.  




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
5 
 (lines  11-19 at page 162 of Record of Appeal)  
Q18 Tadi kamu menyatakan kamu tidak ingat the exect amount 
yang kamu perlu dibuat pembayaran. Adakah kamu boleh 
sahkan jumlah tersebut adalah sepertimana dal am P4(2)?  
A Jumlah P4(2) adalah benar.  5 
 
Q19 Boleh kamu beritahu kepada Mahkamah berapakah jumlah 
yang tertera pada P4(2) itu?  
A RM11,027.20.  
 10 
Q20 Boleh kamu sahkan  kepada Mahkamah kamu telah 
membuat pembayaran berjumlah RM11,027.20?  
A Betul.  
 
(lines  1-7 at page 163 of Record of Appeal)  15 
Q21 Kepada siapakah kamu telah membuat pembayaran 
RM11,027.20?  
A Kepada Adeline . 
 
Q22 Bagaimanakah cara pembayaran yang telah kamu b ayar 20 
kepada Adeline sebany ak RM11,027.20?  
A Secara tunai.  
 
[12] Referring to the above testimonies of PW  8, the learned Sessions 
Court Judge  in her grounds said that PW  8 was actually led to say that 25 
he had paid RM 11,207.20 as stated in P 4(2). PW 8 first said that he 
cannot actually remember the  exact amount but he was shown P 4(2) 
which is the service estimate and he was asked if he had paid the sum 
of RM11,027.20, he said yes.  




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
6 
 [13] I am in agreement with the learned Sessions Court Judge  that PW  
8&#8217;s testimony must be treated with caution. This is in view of the fact that 
he has sent vehicle SAA8886W for rep airs to FM Autohaus Sdn. Bhd.  
many times . 
(lines  6-11 at page 165 of the Record of Appeal)  5 
Q1 Kamu boleh ingat berapa kali kamu pernah menghantar 
SAA8886W untuk repair di FM Auto Hous?  
A Tidak.  
 
Q2 Maknanya kamu pernah hantar banyak kali?  10 
A Ya. 
 
[14] PW 8 also cannot  remember when he actually paid the sum 
RM11,027.20 to the Accused.  
(lines 18 -20 at page 163 of the Record of Appeal)  15 
Q25 Adakah kamu  masih ingat bilakah tarikh kamu membuat 
pembayaran kepada Adeline sebanyak RM11,027.20?  
A Tidak ingat.  
 
[15] Further, PW  8&#8217;s testimony also contradicted the other witnesses&#8217; 20 
evidence on service estimate and Tax Invoice. As stated by PW  9             
(anot her customer in relation to the 1st charge for vehicle no. JMW 
4883), you would only pay after you receive the Tax Invoice. The tax 
invoice will state the actual work that has been done on the car as per 
PW11&#8217;s evidence.  25 
 
 
 
 




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
7 
 [16] So if PW  8 make any payme nt to  the Accused , he would have 
received a Tax Invoice first which would show the actual repair and work 
done on his car. And only after receiving the Tax Invoice would he pay 
the company. He will not pay the amount of RM11,000 .00 first. 
 5 
[17] Why would PW 8 pay the sum of RM11,027.20 when the                  
Tax Invoice (which was supposed to be the final bill as confirmed by 
other witnesses) only stated the sum RM1,547.60 [Exhibit P 4 (3)] ?  
 
[18] And PW  8 himself had admitted that he received this Tax Invoice. 10 
Why didn &#8217;t he asked the Accused to why should he pay the sum of 
RM11,027.20 when the final bill is only RM1,547.60? No explanation at 
all was offered by the witness to clarify this contradiction. Surely he 
would not have paid the sum of RM11,027.20 when the final bill is only 
RM1,547.60.  15 
 
[19] There was no evidence to conclusively confirm that the amount of 
repair done on SAA8886W amounted to RM11,027.60 and the Job Card 
was not produced in Court.  
 20 
[20] It is important to prove how much was actually payable to the 
Company in respect of SAA8886V. If it is the prosecution&#8217;s case that the 
sum of RM11,027.20 was payable to the company, then the prosecution 
must prove that the amount of repair done on SAA8886W was indeed 
RM11,027.20. It must be remembered that the charge  stated the money 25 
purportedly taken by the Respondent as &#8220;harta syarikat&#8221;. So the 
prosecution must prove that the money belonged to FM Autohaus     
Sdn. Bhd. . The prosecution must prove that the amount of repair done 
on SAA8886V was indeed RM11,027.20.  




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
8 
 [21] Clearly , there is a material gap in the Prosecution&#8217;s case. I t has 
been confirmed by many of the prosecution&#8217;s own witnesses that the                   
Job Card and the technician report would conclusively confirm what kind 
or work was done on the said vehic le and what kind of parts were 
installed in the car.  5 
 
[22] The CEO of FM Autohaus  Sdn. Bhd. , PW  11 had confirmed that a 
service estimate is not a final bill.  
(lines  1-8 at page 231 of Record of Appeal)  
Q13 Setuju kalau  saya katakan tax invoice/final invoi ce ini 10 
hend aklah berdasarkan work done yang telah dibuat ke atas 
kereta tersebut?  
A Setuju.  
 
Q14 Maknanya jumlah di dalam tax invoice tidak semestinya 15 
sama dengan jumlah di dalam service estimate, setuju?  
A Setuju.  
 
[23] PW11 had also confirmed that P 4(1) and (2)  are the service 
estimate for SAA886W.  20 
(lines  1-4 at page 204 of Record of Appeal)  
Q41 Saya tunjukan kamu kepada P4(1) dan (2). Dokumen 
service estimate ini adalah dokumen apa?  
A Ini adalah dokumen service estimate  yang telah dikeluarkan 
untuk kereta BMW E60 SAA8886W . 25 
 
 
 
 




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
9 
 [24] To this t he learned Sessions Court Judge  had rightly stated in he r 
grounds that Job card and technician  report would conclusively  
confirmed what kind or work was done on the said vehicle and what 
parts were install in the car to determine the final bill invoice that was 
paid by PW  8. To this she referred to the testimonies of PW  11: 5 
(lines  6-9 at page 229  of Record of Appeal)  
Q5 Bila se suatu kereta dihantar ke FM Auto Haus untuk 
dibaikpulih, satu job card akan dikeluarkan untuk kereta 
tersebut, setuju?  
A Ya, betul.  10 
 
(lines 18 -22 at page 229 of Record of Appeal)  
Q8 Setelah pembaikanpulih/repair telah dibuat ke atas sesuatu 
kereta maka technician  yang membuat repair tersebut 
hendaklah mengisi job card tentang kerja  pembaikanp ulih 15 
yang telah dibuat ataupun work done, setuju?  
A  Setuju.  
 
(lines 8 -12 at page 230 of Record of Appeal)  
Q10  Dan jikalau technician tersebut memasukkan parts ke dalam 20 
kereta ya ng dibaiki maka technician tersebut hend aklah 
memcatatkan sedemikian seb agai work done didalam job 
card?  
A Ya 
(lines 20 -22 at page 230 of Record of Appeal)  25 
Q12 Tetapi apa yang technician repair atau masukkan parts ke 
dalam kereta contohnya hendaklah dicatit di dalam job card?  
A Setuju.  
 




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
10 
 (lines 18 -22 at page 231 of Record of Appeal)  
Q17 Untuk megesahkan apakah repair yang telah dibuat dan 
apakah parts yang telah dimasukkan ke dalam kereta, 
dokumen yang terbaik untuk mendapatkan maklumat ini 
adalah job card, setuju?  5 
A Setuju.  
 
[25] Therefore, t he Job Card and the t echnician repo rt is crucial as it 
would have confirmed  what kind of work was done and therefore how 
much is truly payable to the Company FM Autohaus Sdn. Bhd.                     10 
The amount of RM11,027.20 in P4(2) as the document shows is only 
service estimate  for SAA8886W . 
 
[26] As the P rosecut ion failed to adduce the Job Card and the 
Technician Report for vehicle SAA8886W, the learned Sessions Court 15 
Judge  was right in invoking adverse inference under Section 114(g) of 
the Evidence Act against the prosecution for failing to produce these two 
documents.  
 
[27] The burden is always on the prosecution to prove its case beyond 20 
reasonable doubt. As stated above, t here are doubts in this case as to 
the sum of money stated in the 2nd charge is given to the Accused and 
also whether the money belonged to the Company. There is no 
evidence which can conclusively confirmed both facts.  
 25 
 
 
 




[BKI-42LB -7/7 of 2019 ] 
(Public Prosecutor v. Adeline Casimir Yapp ) 
11 
 [28] At the end of the prosecution case, if a prima facie had been made 
out and the Accused wishes to remain silent, then the evidence must be 
enough for the court to convict the Accused. That means after the 
prosecution case, there shouldn&#8217;t be any doubts in the prosecution case. 
If there are doubts, then the Accused must be acquitted.  5 
 
CONCLUSION  
[29] For the above reasons, t he order of discharged and acquitted by 
the learned Sessions Court Judge  for the 2nd charge is affirmed.  The 
appeal is therefore dismissed.  10 
 
 
 
-sgd- 
AMELATI PARNELL  15 
Judicial Commissioner  
High Court Kota Kinabalu  
Sabah  
 
Date of Delivering of Ruling: 26rd April 2021  20 
 
 
 
For the Appellant:  Mr. Rustam Bin Sanip  
    Deputy Public Prosecutor  25 
    Jabatan Peguam Negara, Negeri Sabah  
    Kota Kinabalu, Sabah  
For the Respondent:  Mr. Rizwandean Bukhary Bin M Borhan  
Messrs. Yusri &amp; Rizwan  
    Sabah  30</page></document>